There's no chance you'd get into any college with your standard score.
以你那種爛成績數值 這世上沒有你能上的大學啦
Don't say that.
我不管
I want to go to the same place as Naomi Kawashima.
我要跟川島直美唸同一所學校
You mean AGU?
青山學院大學？
You wouldn't even make it into their kindergarten, silly!
你這麼笨連幼稚園 都上不了啦，蠢貨！
If I don't go to college,
要是不去大學
I can't become Miss Campus or appear on All Night Fuji.
我就當不了校園小姐 也上不了《通宵富士》
I'll take the back door route to Ferris if I have to.
靠關係也行，我想進菲利斯
You're her mother. Tell her.
你勸勸她吧，這位媽媽
I'm not her mother.
我不是她母親
I thought you married her father.
我還以為你是她爸的再婚對象
Absolutely not. That's not even funny--
怎麼可能，別胡說了 就算是玩笑也不行…
Father.
爸
No. You're not getting it, do you?
不是啦，你沒聽懂我說的吧
You're the father.
你才是小渚的父親吧？
Yes.
是的
But you're my father.
不過你是我爸啊
Your daughter wanted me to talk to her father, so here I am.
令嬡希望我來見她父親 所以我才來的
I mean, sure, I'm a father too.
雖然我也是個爸爸沒錯
I've got a daughter as well.
畢竟我也有一個女兒
-Father. -Weren't you listening?
-爸 -你有在聽嗎？
Call me father one more time, and who knows what might happen!
你再叫一次“爸”試試看 我不敢保證會做出什麼事喔！
I sent you something.
我傳給你了
Huh?
什麼？
Listen, Ogawa, with your looks,
小川啊，靠你這張漂亮的臉
you could find a husband without education.
就算學歷不高，至少還嫁得出去啦
Excuse me, are you serious?
等一下，老師，你是認真的嗎？
If she wasn't pretty,
她如果是醜女
I'd advise her to study hard for a national university.
我當然會叫她拼命念書 考上國立大學
I graduated from one!
我畢業於國立大學！
Anyway, that's a terrible thing to say as an educator!
而且太扯了，你身為一位教師
Misogyny, education-based discrimination, lookism,
居然輕視女性、學歷歧視、以貌取人
and what else?
還有什麼來著？
But I won't attract any guys at Maharaja unless I'm in college.
女大學生去MAHARAJA 迪斯可舞廳才會受歡迎
Oh, Junko.
天哪，純子
This is Junko.
這不是純子嗎？
It's Junko.
是純子沒錯
You go by her first name?
你為何要直呼其名？
Huh?
什麼？
Hold up, what's going on here, huh?
等一下，這是怎麼回事？是怎樣？
What?
不會吧？這是…
Who's the kid in her arms?
她抱著的小鬼是誰？
That's me.
就是我
Nagisa is Junko's daughter.
渚是純子的女兒
You're my granddaughter?
是我的孫女？
Hey, Grandpa.
外公
Father.
爸
I'm your father-in-law.
我是你岳父呢
And I'm your grandpa.
我還是你外公
What the hell?!
不會吧？
Don't bother. I'll do it myself.
不用啦，我自己來
He just had heart surgery, so his breathing isn't stable yet.
他剛做完心臟手術，呼吸還不太穩定
Got it.
這樣啊
So you're my granddaughter.
你居然是我孫女
Barkeep, did you know this?
老闆，你早就知道了嗎？
You should've said, stupid geezer!
那就早點說啊，臭老頭！
That's why we felt tinglings when we tried some hanky-panky.
難怪試圖做那檔子事 就會有觸電的感覺
You tried some hanky-panky?
你試圖做那檔子事？
-Sorry about that. -No worries.
-非常抱歉 -別這麼說
It would've been messed up to make out with my grandkid.
我可不能對孫女出手，又不是禽獸
It was a near miss.
差點就越界了
I was careless too.
我也有錯，我實在太不小心了
You were.
是啊
You were really careless.
你真的太輕率了
You made your grandpa fall for you.
害外公都有那個意思
By the way, did she tell you that I'm from the past?
你有聽她說了嗎？我是活在過去的人
I got here on a time machine.
是搭乘時光機來到現代
Yes, sort of.
有，多少有聽說
Speaking of 1986, the prime minister back then was…
1986年的總理大臣是…
Nakasone.
-中曾根 -是喔
I see.
原來如此
So Junko married you.
所以純子會嫁給你啊
I'm afraid so.
不好意思
Beats her getting together with that punk Mutchy.
至少她沒和阿睦那小子在一起
So, where's Junko now?
所以純子現在在哪？
Hm? What's the matter?
嗯？怎麼了？
She couldn't make it?
她今天沒來嗎？
Don't tell me…
該不會…
Well?
什麼？
They split up.
他們離婚了
They got divorced, and my mother is living overseas now.
媽離婚後在國外生活
Right?
對不對？
I'm afraid so.
很抱歉
I see.
這樣啊
The Junko I know is still in high school, so it's all hard to imagine.
我知道的純子還只是高二生 所以很難想像
I see.
是喔
But marriages can be complicated.
不過夫妻關係本來就很複雜
Even Shingo Yamashiro split with Hiromi Hanazono after 20 years.
山城新伍還不是 跟在一起20年的花園浩美離婚了
Six years later, he tied the knot with her again.
6年後他們又會再婚
He did?
真的假的？
And eight years after that,
過了8年之後
they divorced once more.
兩人又會再離婚
Shingo's quite the character, huh?
新伍還真是不容小覷
Maybe you'll have another shot with Junko then.
那你說不定也能跟純子復合呢
Where exactly is she?
她去了國外的哪裡？
What's your deal?
搞什麼？
You had more to say about Shingo Yamashiro.
關於山城新伍的八卦 倒是說得那麼起勁
FRANCE, PROVENCE REGION
（法國，普羅旺斯地區）
She's…
她在…
in the Provence region.
普羅旺斯地區那一帶
In southern France.
就是法國南部
Right?
對不對？
She said it was her dream to open a bouillabaisse shop.
她的夢想是在南法 開一間馬賽魚湯餐廳
Why don't you tell me how you got to know each other?
我想知道你們是怎麼認識的
You mean Junko and me?
我和令媛嗎？
Yeah, tell me what you know about her after she finished high school.
是啊，高中畢業後她在做什麼？ 把你知道的都告訴我
Are you okay?
你沒問題吧？
I heard she was a bit of a rebel in high school.
我聽說她高中時很叛逆
That's an understatement.
當時真的很誇張
They call her the Downtown Junko Mihara.
大家都叫她“下町的三原順子”
She's a Diet member now.
她現在是國會議員喔
Who? Junko Mihara?
你說誰？三原順子嗎？
You're kidding me. After releasing "Sexy Night"?
不敢相信 唱那首“Sexy Night”的人？
In 2007, she divorced Happy Happy, formerly Koala, and…
她在2007年跟Happy Happy離婚 也就是名為Koala的人…
Forget about Mihara.
別管三原了
Tell me about Ogawa. Junko Ogawa.
我要聽小川的事 繼續說小川純子的故事
In her third year of high school, she cut ties with her delinquent friends.
她高三的時候 跟家鄉學壞的朋友斷絕關係
She turned over a new leaf,
發奮圖強，努力唸書
and nailed the college entrance exam upon graduation.
應屆考上大學
Is that so?
是嗎？
Good.
很好…
I knew she had it in her. She's not dumb.
想做就做得到嘛，她腦袋又不笨
Female college students were all the rage.
當時有一股女大生潮流
She gathered attention wherever she went.
她在各處都很受歡迎
And she got scouted by a modeling agency.
後來便被模特兒公司挖掘出道
Nice.
不錯喔
How about we get rid of the shirt soon?
現在把上衣脫下來吧
What?
什麼？
Very funny. No way.
別開玩笑了啦，我才不拍那種照片
I was just joking!
逗你的啦！對吧？
All right, let's hit Roppongi!
好，我帶你去六本木吧！
This way. Follow me.
來這邊，跟我來
Here we go.
嘿咻
If you're pals with the black-suited, you get special treatment.
跟黑衣領班打好關係 可以得到很多好處喔
Mr. Noshima, who's this cute chick with you?
能島先生，今天怎麼 帶這麼漂亮的小妞來？
This is Junko, a college student. It's her debut at a disco.
她是女大生的純子 是第一次來迪斯可舞廳
Is that so?
是這樣啊？
Let me treat you to a drink, then.
那我請你喝一杯
No way. Are you sure?
天哪，真的可以嗎？
Excuse me? That rosé is my order.
慢著，那是我點的粉紅酒耶
Hang tight. I'll bring you one shortly.
等一下嘛，我馬上就拿過來
That's not the problem!
不是那個問題！
I paid a hefty cover charge, and you serve this girl first?
我都付了大筆的錢 還被排在這小女孩後面
It's not fair!
太離譜了吧！
Shut up! Who cares about your rosé?
少囉唆！什麼粉紅酒啦？
If you're acting high and mighty, you should drink pickle sauce instead!
仗著是貴賓就態度囂張 你只配喝紅薑汁啦！
That's me.
那就是我
Sorry, who?
不好意思，你說誰？
This.
這張照片裡的人
I was young and fearless, rocking a black suit at a disco.
我當時年輕氣盛 在迪斯可舞廳當黑衣領班
Those were the days.
真令人懷念呢
You usually keep a hint of your youth,
一般來說，不管過了多久
no matter how much time goes by.
還是看得出當年的影子
I don't?
不像我嗎？
No, not even a bit.
一點都不像
This is someone else.
這根本是另一個人
I agree. I felt like I was being lied to since I was a child.
我也從小就懷疑是不是被父親騙了
Very well.
我明白了
Let me use the Wi-Fi here.
借我連一下無線網路
Dad, don't.
爸，別鬧了
If you see this, I know you will believe me.
只要看了這個，爸一定會相信我的
Newbies wore dark red, waiters wore blue, and top waiters wore yellow.
當時舞廳的新人是穿紅色 服務生是穿藍色
Like that, the staff was ranked by color.
依照階級穿不同顏色的衣服
When I became a captain, I finally got to wear black.
我當上領班後，才終於能穿黑衣
The highest rank was champion.
最頂端的則稱被為霸主
Junko,
純子
if I become a champion, will you marry me?
若我成為霸主，你願意跟我結婚嗎？
Of course.
當然願意
But Yuzu, what color comes after black?
不過阿讓，黑色再上去是什麼顏色？
This is Yuzuru Inushima.
他是犬島讓
I'm going to marry this man.
我要跟他結婚
What are you?
你是怎樣？
An alien?
是外星人嗎？
I'm from Hyogo.
我是兵庫人
Whatever. I can't marry her off to a guy with such wide shoulders.
誰管你啊，我不能把女兒 交給肩膀寬得誇張的男人
Oh, come on.
為什麼啊？
And what's with your outfit?
還有，你穿的那是什麼衣服？
There's barely any fabric on you.
布料面積太少了吧
It's called the one-length bodycon look.
現在流行剪齊髮配緊身洋裝啦
Father, I love Junko.
爸，我深愛著純子小姐
Don't cut in, shoulder pads.
別來攪局，你這個墊肩的傢伙
I played around since I turned 16 and slept with over 400 women.
我從16歲就是個花花公子 曾與四百位以上的女性共度良宵
But I believe all that experience was just practice for meeting Junko.
那些全都只是為了 在遇到純子小姐前積攢的練習經驗
That's how crazy in love I am with her.
我現在只對令媛一心一意
What parent would be happy to hear that?
有哪個父親聽到你這樣說會開心？
I mean it. I'll end things with the other women!
我是認真的，我會和其他女人分手
-You haven't yet? -I'll break up with them soon. I promise!
-現在才要分？ -會盡快甩了她們，我保證馬上就分
Shut up.
你閉嘴
End it with the other girls,
你跟前女友斷乾淨
ditch those shoulder pads, and then we'll talk.
拆掉墊肩，再來找我吧
I can't…
恕我…
promise you that.
無法答應
Yuzu?
阿讓？
These shoulder pads represent being a champion.
墊肩可是霸主的象徵
They're the essence of Roppongi.
代表六本木的靈魂
I can't let them go.
我絕不能拆掉墊肩
My name means yield, but I won't yield these.
雖然我名叫“讓” 但這一點我不會讓步
Then, forget it. It's not happening.
那你滾吧，我不可能把女兒交給你
Is that so?
不可能嗎？
Yeah.
不可能
I understand.
我明白了
Allow me to use your cassette tape player.
我借一下磁帶播放機
Yuzu, what are you doing?
阿讓，你要做什麼？
I have to show your father how serious I am.
只好讓爸看看我的決心了
Please let me marry Junko.
請把純子小姐交給我吧
This is how committed I am.
我用這支舞表明心意
What on earth?
那是什麼舞啦？
It's a dance asking for your blessing.
請求你讓令媛嫁給我之舞
Father, do you see?
爸，我的誠意就如你所見
Please believe me.
爸，相信我吧
-Go home! -It's too late.
-滾回去！ -已經太晚了
I'm pregnant.
我懷孕了
That's me.
肚子裡的就是我
You bastard!
你這王八蛋！
What the hell have you done?
你這混帳幹了什麼好事？
Junko, apologize to your mom!
純子，去跟媽媽道歉！
Calm down, Mr. Ogawa! Please!
你冷靜點，小川先生，拜託！
Sorry. My bad.
對不起，是我不好
The Junko I know is still in high school.
因為在我心中純子還只是個高二生
It's all right.
沒關係
That wasn't my first time.
這是你第二次壓倒我
It was a first for me.
對我來說是第一次
Right.
對了
It hasn't happened yet.
這是未來才要發生的事
So this alien is coming to visit my place in the future, huh?
在未來的某天 這個外星人小子就會到我家來？
How many years from now?
這是幾年後的事？
It was when Junko was in her fourth year of college.
純子大四的時候
Four years from now?
四年後？
Just four years?
只剩四年了
I don't know if I can keep my cool.
我撐得住嗎？到時能保持冷靜嗎？
You don't have to.
爸要發飆也沒關係
I suppose not.
我也那麼認為
It's this guy, right?
畢竟登門拜訪的可是這傢伙
I'm sure I can be just as furious at him.
我有十足的信心 能像剛剛那樣大發雷霆
Third baseman!
三壘手！
You didn't give our marriage your blessing.
爸不認同我們的這段婚姻
When we brought Nagisa to see you,
有次我們帶著渚去見你
Shall we go, Nagisa?
渚，我們回家吧
Grandpa's too busy.
外公他好像很忙呢
When the economy bubble burst,
隨著泡沫經濟崩壞
the disco industry also began to decline.
舞廳產業也逐漸沒落
So, I headed back to Kobe to manage the family business.
於是我下定決心回神戶繼承家業
I thought of making a suit for you as a gift.
當時我想要做一套西裝送給爸
I wrote you a letter, asking you to come in for measurements.
所以寫了一封信，邀你過來量尺寸
I included a bullet train ticket
附上了新幹線的車票
and I invited you to come…
跟信一同寄出去…
I didn't go, did I?
我一定沒去吧？
I can be pretty stubborn.
畢竟我是個老頑固
-Are you good? -I'm fine.
-你還好嗎？ -我沒事
You know what?
好啦
I'll go to Kobe.
我去神戶就是了
Wait,
等等
I shouldn't go.
我不能去
This is so complicated.
真是複雜
This is the past for you, but for me, it's the future.
對你來說是過去 對我而言卻是未來的事
Anyway, why did you and Junko break up?
之後你怎麼會跟純子離婚？
Well…
那是因為…
My father was unfaithful.
要怪父親愛偷吃
I suspected as much.
我想也是啦
He's a champion, after all.
他是霸主嘛
My lack of virtue is to blame.
都是我缺乏德性害的
So, who with?
對象是什麼人？
The first person…
第一位是…
was a life insurance saleswoman.
壽險業務員
Her name?
叫什麼名字？
Soko Fujii.
藤井聰子小姐
She was a sharp girl.
是位聰明的女孩
And the second?
第二位呢？
T-The second?
第二位？
You mentioned "first."
誰叫你剛才說了“第一位”
She was a yoga instructor.
是瑜珈教練
Her name?
叫什麼名字？
Does her name concern you?
你很在意名字嗎？
Um…
這個嘛…
It was Uber…
羽宇馬…
Itsuko Uuba.
羽宇馬逸子小姐
Uuba is written using the Kanji for feather, universe, and horse.
“羽毛”的羽、“宇宙”的宇 “馬匹”的馬，羽宇馬
-And the third-- -You can stop.
-第三位… -夠了
I've heard enough.
我已經聽夠了
Right.
我想也是
After the divorce, I moved to Tokyo and started a tailor shop in Chofu.
離婚後我來到東京 在調布開了一間裁縫店
But I fell ill last year and…
不過身體狀況在去年急轉直下…
Now, Masato, him, and I are living together.
現在他和我，還有正人住在一起
Did you compensate her?
你有付贍養費嗎？
Absolutely.
當然有
With that money, she fulfilled her long-cherished dream of…
她拿著那筆錢 為了實現長年的夢想…
She went to Brazil to pursue her dream of becoming a samba dancer.
也就是成為森巴舞者，前往了巴西
Not southern France?
不是南法嗎？
She mastered samba and now runs a bouillabaisse shop, right?
她一邊精進森巴舞藝 一邊經營馬賽魚湯店，對不對？
That's right.
正是如此
So Junko's doing well, huh?
看來純子過得很好
That's all I need to know.
只要知道那點，我就滿足了
I'm sorry, Nagisa.
抱歉啦，小渚
Your grandpa was too stubborn to hold you.
外公個性比較彆扭 當年甚至沒有抱你
Do it now.
現在抱吧
What?
什麼？
Wait a minute.
不行吧…
Really?
可以嗎？
Absolutely. Junko would be pleased as well.
當然可以，純子也會高興的
She's my grandkid.
她是我孫女
That's why this is fine.
因為是孫女所以沒關係
Grandpa.
外公
Nagisa.
渚
C-Come on!
為什麼啦？
Akitsu, this won't do.
秋津，果然不合身
The sleeves are too long. Can I cut them?
袖子太長了，可以剪掉嗎？
Just roll them up.
捲起來就好了啊
Like this.
就像這樣
Can't I wear a polo shirt? I'm just a part-timer.
穿POLO衫不行嗎？ 反正不是正式雇用
No way.
不行
The new recruits will look down on you.
你會被新進員工瞧不起喔
Hello?
喂？
Can you hear me?
聽得到嗎？
Sorry, Sakae.
抱歉，紗加惠小姐
Anyway,
情況就如你看到的
let the principal know
請幫我轉達給校長
I might be able to return before the midterm exam.
我應該會在期中考之前回去
Got it.
知道了
Junko, what are you wearing?
純子？你怎麼穿成這樣？
Huh?
什麼？
Just trying to make sure the new students don't look down on me.
為了給新生一個下馬威啊
I nearly mistook you for Bull Nakano.
還以為你是藍面中野咧
But my socks have a Dalmatian pattern.
但襪子是大麥町花紋喔
What did you call it?
這要怎麼形容？
Gap-moe.
“反差萌”
That's lame.
好俗氣
My roommate says you look lame. Go change.
我室友也說很俗氣，快換掉吧
This gives off vibes of a famous actress' delinquent past
她這樣很像知名女演員
Huh? Who the hell are you? I'll kill you!
啥？你是誰啊？小心我宰了你！
Junko, my arms are dead.
學姐，我舉不動了
Sako…
佐高家…
What are you doing?
你在做什麼？
The call network.
打給聯絡網
We have a PTA meeting today.
今天有家長會要開
There's no one called Sako in my class.
班上沒有叫佐高的同學喔
What?
什麼？
April is a hectic period for TV stations as it's a transitional period.
電視台在4月迎來過渡期 所以大家都手忙腳亂
I got Sakae to extend my leave.
我拜託紗加惠小姐幫我延長休假期間
Premium Saturday!
《優質星期六》！
I will nonchalantly make your Saturday noon premium.
我會若無其事地讓週六午間變優質
Don't miss it!
敬請期待！
Look who's full of himself.
看他得意洋洋的樣子
Let the principal know
請幫我轉達給校長
I might be able to return before the midterm exam.
我應該會在期中考之前回去
That's it.
以上是他的留言
Oh, well.
就隨他去吧
It seems the baseball club is more relaxed without him.
棒球社的成員也練得很自在
If the parents ask, we can say he's off for training.
如果有家長問起，就說他是去進修吧
Mr. Yasumori, can I take a look at the PTA's expenses and past ledgers?
安森老師，關於家長會的營運費 可以讓我看看以前的帳本嗎？
We don't have those.
沒有那種東西
We gather operating fees at the start of the school year.
營運費會在每學年初收取
When we run out, we ask for more.
不夠的話會再次收取
And if there's extra…
有剩的話…
We go, "we have some left over."
就說一句“有剩呢”
Right?
對不對？
Yes, and then we use it to buy snacks and juice and stuff.
是啊，就拿來買些零食或果汁
Are you seriously spending the parents' money so carelessly?
重要的家長會費 居然用得如此隨便？
We get receipts for our expenses and keep them in a notebook, of course.
有花費的部分一定會索取收據 貼在筆記本裡
And we reconcile the books at the end of the year.
然後在每學年的尾聲核對收支
And if they don't add up?
如果對不起來呢？
We simply go, "They didn't add up," and find money elsewhere.
就說一句“對不起來呢” 從別的地方挪用
That's a cover-up!
這是在隱瞞吧！
A cover-up?
這算隱瞞？
We've been doing this for decades.
幾十年來，我們都是這麼做的
The books don't add up because some parent is overspending.
一定是有哪位家長濫用 收支才對不起來吧
Well…
關於那點…
I can't investigate that.
我們沒辦法追究
It's basically everyone's money, after all.
畢竟這筆錢是屬於每個人的
Right?
對不對？
Um… I've got some work to attend to.
我還有工作要忙
Wait, Mr. Yasumori!
等一下，安森老師！
The call network. The person after me is a Sako.
關於聯絡網，我們家後面是佐高家
Sako…
佐高啊…
is a truant.
拒絕上學
You mean an absentee?
那名學生沒去上學？
I guess you wouldn't know.
向坂太太不知道吧
It started last year in the second term.
是從去年第二學期開始的
We've visited his home, called him up, and tried everything.
校方有登門拜訪 也打電話聯繫，用盡各種方法
But his parents asked us to stop.
最後連學生的家長也放棄了
They wanted their son's name removed from the register.
還說以此事為恥 要求把佐高這名字從學生名單刪掉
Another cover-up.
又隱瞞了
There's nothing we can do.
我們也束手無策啊
Truancy is a family issue.
學生拒絕上學是家庭問題
No, it's not.
我不同意
Absenteeism is a problem society needs to address together.
學生不上學 是整體社會該一起解決的問題
It's truancy.
是“拒絕上學”才對
It's absenteeism.
是“不上學”
Kids aren't absent from school for just one reason.
學生不來上學不是單一因素造成的
Sometimes it's psychological, emotional, or social.
有心理、情緒、社會等方面的因素
Some kids want to go but physically can't.
有的孩子雖然想來 但身體就是動不了
You can't assume they're playing truant, so you shouldn't use the word "truancy."
不能完全斷定就是“拒絕上學”
the Ministry of Justice submits a report on absentee children in Heisei 1.
平成元年，法務省將會提出 關於“不上學兒童”的調查報告書
Mr. Yasumori, you can be ahead of your time.
安森老師，你有機會走在時代的前線
Heisei?
平成？
Ugh, I'm so upset.
可惡，氣死我了
I shouldn't have joined the PTA board.
早知道就不要當什麼家長會的幹部
If only I could use social media.
這種時候要是有社群媒體就方便了
When you were taking time off, you were texting your friends on Insta.
你休學的期間 也有跟同學傳Instagram嘛
What? You weren't going to school?
什麼？阿清也沒去學校？
He stopped going to school in the second term as well.
跟他的情況一模一樣 從第二學期就不去上學
He started going again after coming here, but now he's like this.
來到這裡總算願意去上學了 雖然是好事，但居然搞成這樣子
No way!
不會吧！
So it's thanks to me!
那都要歸功於我！
It's thanks to you and boobs.
要歸功給純子跟胸部
He must be lonely,
佐高同學一定很孤單
being alone all day.
整天都是一個人
And without social media or subs.
也沒有社群媒體或串流平台 可以消磨時間
And no free schools either.
也沒有自由學校可以去
What are those?
那是什麼？
They're privately run schools for kids who don't go to regular school.
為了不上學的孩子而設立的學校 是由民間發起的
Not bad, future.
未來還真不錯
Hey, Kiyoshi, why don't you reach out to this kid?
阿清，你去跟那學生聊天嘛
No way. We've never even met.
又沒見過面，沒辦法聊啦
It actually might make it easier for him.
說不定這樣對方更好開口啊
But I don't even know what his interests are.
不過我又不知道對方的喜好
That tasted horrible!
有夠難吃的！
Hey!
怎麼這樣說？
I could use something refreshing.
好想去暢快一下
It's me, Mutchy!
阿睦來囉！
Anyone up for a ride on my Honda CBX along the shoreline?
誰要坐上我的本田CBX 去海邊的衝浪大道兜風啊？
I'm game!
我要去！
I wanted to go with Junko, not you.
比起阿姨，我比較想載純子耶
Why not? You should take her.
有什麼關係嘛，你就載她去嘛
Come on…
別開玩笑了…
Shut up!
吵死了！
Be quiet.
都給我安靜！
This show kicked off today.
這是今天開播的節目
It's Yuri Osawa's Yu Yu Wide.
《大澤悠里的悠悠廣角》
-It's from Scandal in Katsushika. -That's me!
-葛飾區的緋聞來信 -是我！
I sent that in!
這是我寄出去的！
-They're reading my postcard. -"Hello, Yuri."
-唸到我的明信片了 -“你好，悠里先生
"I'd like to request 'Anoko to Scandal' by Checkers, please."
我想點播方格子樂團的 《阿諾可都斯堪達爾》”
Let's give it a listen.
那就開始播放
Where to?
你想去哪裡？
I don't know. Anywhere you want.
沒任何想法，去哪都可以
Actually, go to Matsudo Midori Park!
還是去松戶綠公園吧！
You totally had a place in mind!
你早就決定好了嘛！
Hurry.
快點
Want one?
要喝嗎？
Yeah. Thanks.
好，謝謝你
Look.
你看
That kid is me.
那女孩就是我
You guys are so stupid, you know that?
你們真是無聊透頂
Apologize!
好好跟人家道歉！
Sakae, it's fine now.
紗加惠，算了啦
No, it's not!
一點都不好
Big kids have bigger problems.
高大的女生也會有煩惱啊
What are you stuffing in there?
你外套裡塞了什麼？
Show me!
拿出來！
When I was a kid, they used to call me PTA.
想起來了 我小時候的綽號是“家長會”
On my way back from cram school,
補習班下課回家的路上
I used to hold public lectures here every day.
每天都在這裡當眾說教
Those are melon buns!
居然是哈密瓜麵包！
That's disrespectful to the baker!
你這樣對麵包店也很失禮！
What?
什麼？
Are you saying that girl is similar to you, old lady?
阿姨，你是指你就像那女生嗎？
Yeah.
對
Shouldn't you just call me "lady" instead of throwing in "old"?
話說一般不會直接叫“阿姨” 會先叫“大姐姐”吧？
If I give you permission to call me "old lady," then go ahead.
等我回說“叫我阿姨就好” 你才能叫吧？
Mind your manners.
這種事不能省略
S-Sorry.
你說得對，抱歉
Apologize now!
快點道歉！
To this girl and the bakery!
向她還有麵包店謝罪！
Things never change, do they?
我真是沒變
Neither me nor society.
這個社會也都沒變
What are you doing?
你在做什麼？
Nothing.
沒什麼
No need to hide it.
不要藏起來嘛
Is it porn? Show me!
是色色的書嗎？讓我看看！
RADIO EXCITE
（《雀躍廣播》）
I thought that Sako might be listening.
我在想佐高同學可能有在聽
To the radio?
聽廣播？
He'd probably ignore my calls.
就算我打電話去，對方大概也不會接
And showing up unannounced might overwhelm him.
突然上門會造成壓力
So, I figured I could reach out via radio.
所以想透過廣播來喊話
That's ridiculously inefficient, you know.
不過這樣效率太差了吧
I know that.
我知道啊
I wish I could message him on Insta or X,
因為我想不到有什麼聯繫方式
without making him feel pressured.
可以像Instagram或X那樣
But this was all I could come up with.
不會造成對方的負擔
Fine. I'll help you.
真拿你沒辦法，我來幫忙吧
Junko…
學姐…
You put your stupid brain to work on this, right?
你雖然笨 但拼命想出了這個方法對吧？
I'm not stupid, you know.
我不笨啦
What's your handle?
筆名要叫什麼？
Mysterious Transfer Student.
“神祕轉學生”
That's lame.
真土啊
Is he in?
他在嗎？
He is.
在裡面
May I have a moment?
現在方便嗎？
COUNSELOR OGAWA FROM HELL
（諮商師，地獄小川）
Sure.
當然…
I saw the ad for PS. He was so full of himself.
我看到《優六》的廣告了 他一副得意洋洋的樣子
Actually, starting this April, I've moved to a different department.
其實我從4月起就轉調到別的部門
RISK MANAGEMENT DEPT.
（風險管理部）
He's the manager of Risk Management. He's on the career track.
他現在是風險管理部部長
I've nominated her as my successor
我讓她接手職位
and handed over the production to the younger team.
把第一線交給年輕人來做
What? You're a producer now, Nagisacchi?
什麼？小渚當上製作人了嗎？
That's a big step up! That calls for a celebration!
這不是大升遷嗎？要好好恭喜你才行
However,
不過呢
we've just had a major scandal involving the main emcee.
那件主持人的醜聞事件才剛發生
I know.
我知道…
Tsutsumin's six affairs, right? Outrageous.
堤哥腳踏六條船的傳聞嘛，真下流
To prevent a similar blunder, I've had talks with the higher-ups.
反省此事後，我們和上層討論過
Moving forward,
決定從今以後
I'm planning to carefully monitor our cast's behavior, not just our staff's.
除了員工以外 對演出者的行為也會加強監控
And I'll be using a location-based service for that.
所以會導入定位服務系統
Are you available after the broadcast on Saturday?
週六收播後，你有時間嗎？
Next week, we've got a Yashima special.
下回是八嶋祭
Get ready for three hours of non-stop karaoke fun!
長達三小時的卡拉OK特集！
Let's hope I make it through alive.
別死啊，長嶋
All right, everyone, let's say it together.
大家跟我一起喊，預備
PS!
《優六》！
Okay, that's it for today!
今天就錄到這裡！
-Well done! -Well done.
-辛苦了！ -大家辛苦了
-Thank you.
-辛苦了 -謝謝
What? What's happening?
什麼？現在要做什麼？
We've installed a GPS app on our cast members' smartphones.
我們在演出者的手機裡 安裝了定位應用程式
With their and their agencies' consent, of course.
本人和經紀公司當然已經同意了
It's to track their movements after the broadcast.
我們會追蹤他們收播後的行蹤
Huh? What is this?
什麼？這是什麼？
Wait, is this allowed??
可以嗎？這樣做可以嗎？
Honestly, we'd rather not resort to this.
其實我們也不想這樣做
But given that some of them are minors,
但是演出者也有未成年人
this serves as a deterrent to avoid any potential trouble.
也有預防出事的嚇阻效果
Unfortunately, it's effective.
很遺憾，這方法是有效的
Better safe than sorry, I suppose.
算是未雨綢繆嗎？
I've spotted someone acting suspiciously.
有一個人形跡可疑
Great observation, Mr. Ogawa. You've got a sharp eye.
不愧是小川先生，眼睛很利
This is indeed
這就是我們頭痛的原因
There he is, Yashiman.
出現了，是嶋哥
Exactly.
沒錯
After the live broadcast on Saturday,
星期六現場直播結束後
Mr. Yashima consistently takes a taxi in the opposite direction of his home.
八嶋先生一定會搭上計程車 往家裡的反方向去
And for some reason, he gets off near the Skytree.
不知為何都在晴空塔附近下車
A man heading to the Skytree alone on a Saturday evening.
男人在星期六傍晚獨自來到晴空塔
Seems fishy, right?
怎麼想都很可疑吧？
That's just your perspective, isn't it? He could be going to a sauna.
那只是你的個人意見啊 他可能是去洗三溫暖
I want to believe him too.
我也想這麼相信
I don't want to jump to conclusions
53歲的資深演員下班不回家
But in these times, it's too late if something happens.
但現在這種時代 等事情發生再挽救就來不及了
Today is the day we'll get to the bottom of this.
今天一定要抓到他的狐狸尾巴
You're doubting him 100%.
你們對他的不信任度是100%耶
We're connected with the field.
現場跟轉播連上了
This is Ujiie, reporting from the field.
我是人在現場的氏家
Mr. Yashima
八嶋先生他啊
is running in circles near the Skytree.
繞著晴空塔附近跑步
Maybe he's lost or…
他可能是迷路了，不然就是…
waiting for someone.
在等某人
He's carrying a suspicious-looking black bag.
他提著可疑的黑色包包
Maybe it contains items used for kinky sex.
是進行變態性行為的道具嗎？
Like whips or handcuffs.
裝鞭子或手銬之類的
He's drinking an energy drink
他喝了能量飲料
and now he's doing squats.
在做深蹲
Is he married?
他有結婚嗎？
Yes, to an actress. She's quite tall.
有，太太是位身材高䠷的女演員
This is an affair, then.
那就是搞婚外情
Huh? What now?
奇怪？怎麼了？
He's making a dash for it!
他忽然全力衝刺，逃走了
Damn it! He just disabled the GPS.
可惡！定位系統被他關掉了
Ujiie, it's on you. Don't let him slip away!
氏家，交給你了，別跟丟！
Mr. Ogawa, do we let this slide?
小川先生，我們應該隱瞞實情嗎？
Or…
還是…
We investigate!
來查證！
What's this? What's the occasion?
幹什麼？你們怎麼了？
Did I win the Galaxy Award? It's too early, huh?
我拿到銀河賞了嗎？會不會太快？
We'll cut to the chase.
我就開門見山地問了
Mr. Yashima, you are
八嶋先生
having an affair.
你在搞婚外情吧？
-No. -Don't lie!
-沒有 -不准說謊！
Quiet.
你好吵喔
Look me in the eye.
看著我的眼睛
Mr. Yashima,
八嶋先生
are you having an affair?
你有在搞婚外情吧？
Yes or no?
有沒有…
No.
沒有
You sound fishy.
太可疑了
Your glasses scream deceit. You lying four-eyes!
那副眼鏡真可疑，眼鏡騙子！
Shut up.
吵死了
Why are you so rude?
你到底是怎樣？真沒禮貌
For a whole month,
在過去的一個月
we've been keeping tabs on you.
我們監視了八嶋先生的行動
What?
什麼？
From 5 to 6 p.m.,
傍晚五點到六點
you were wandering around the Skytree.
你在晴空塔附近徘徊
After that, you turned off your GPS and disappeared.
然後把定位系統關掉，隱藏行蹤
And precisely for two hours…
消失整整兩個小時
You took a break, didn't you?
你是去休息了吧？
You went into a hotel for a break.
上賓館休息了吧？
And after 10 p.m.,
然後十點過後
you returned home acting innocent.
再若無其事地回家
You're guilty.
可以斷定你有罪
Totally guilty.
你罪證確鑿
I'm disappointed, Mr. Yashima.
很遺憾，八嶋先生
Damn.
真頭痛
I didn't want anyone to find out about this.
唯獨這件事我不想讓人知道
There! Yashima confessed!
八嶋招了！
He confessed.
終於承認了
It's not an affair. I was playing kendama.
才不是婚外情，是練劍玉啦！
Kendama?
劍玉？
Take a good look at the sign.
你們仔細看店面招牌
We investigate.
確認一下
KENDAMA CAFE
（劍玉咖啡廳）
A kendama cafe?
“劍玉咖啡廳”？
Mr. Kurita,
栗田先生
remember what you said?
你上次這麼說過吧？
About what's appropriate for a Saturday afternoon.
“適合在星期六下午看的…”
It's not your self-centered excuses!
不是你自以為是的辯解
It's Mr. Yashima's kendama!
而是八嶋先生的劍玉挑戰！
Your words struck a chord in me.
那句話莫名地觸動了我
And it hit me.
“這樣啊
That you were genuinely thinking
這個人是認真致力於製作
about creating a program that fits into people's lives.
符合觀眾生活型態的節目內容”
So, I will take it seriously too
那我也要認真面對
and be a guy who is appropriate for a Saturday afternoon.
成為配得上星期六下午的男人
Right after I made that vow came the three-hour karaoke special.
才剛在內心發誓 不久後就要主持卡拉OK三小時特集
Simply singing wouldn't cut it.
我認為唱歌撐不了三小時
Please show me the ropes!
請多關照
Hey, pull yourself together!
喂，你要認真練！
Focus and keep your eye on the ball!
-集中精神，好好看著球！ -好
Oops, sorry!
糟了，不好意思！
-You're getting better though. -Right.
-跟之前比進步很多了 -是啊
-Try tossing the ball straight up. -Okay.
-球往正上方拋 -好
And catch it softly with your hand.
手反彈回來的時候接住
Well,
這樣的話
what about those squats?
深蹲又是怎麼回事？
I was mentally practicing.
是想像練習
You guys have got it all wrong.
大家都誤會了對吧？
Kendama isn't just about using your arms.
劍玉不是靠手腕在玩
It's all in the knees. That's the key.
是靠膝蓋，重要的是膝蓋
I'd rather keep my efforts to myself.
我不想讓人知道我在背後默默努力啦
-You're so earnest. -Huh?
-太正經了 -啥？
-You're earnest four-eyes. -What?
-你太正經了吧！ -你說什麼？
Mr. Yashima, I totally misjudged you.
八嶋先生，是我誤會了
I'm sorry for doubting you.
很抱歉懷疑你的為人
Mr. Yashima, I beg your forgiveness.
八嶋先生，請接受我的賠罪
Please lift your head.
快把頭抬起來
I'm sorry for saying you were into kinky stuff.
抱歉說你是變態 還說你會進行變態性行為
That's news to me, but no hard feelings.
那我可沒聽說，不過我沒生氣啦
YASHIMA KARAOKE SPECIAL
（八嶋卡拉OK特集）
This is perfect for a Saturday afternoon.
星期六下午好適合看這節目
Huh?
這是什麼？
MR. ICHIRO OGAWA
（小川市郎先生）
It's from Nagisa's father, right?
是渚小姐的父親寄的吧
I WILL TAILOR A SUIT FOR YOU PLEASE COME ANYTIME
（我想為爸量身訂做一套西裝 歡迎隨時來訪）
I guess I'll go.
我就去吧
When my daughter returns from France, she'll laugh if she sees me like this.
等女兒從法國回來 我可不想穿成這樣被她嘲笑
Huh?
什麼？
Father.
爸
You came.
你來了啊
May I come in?
方便打擾一下嗎？
Of course.
請進
To the second floor, please.
請上二樓
This way.
請來這邊
Okay.
好
This is for taking measurements. Please change into this.
這是量尺寸用的，請穿上
Here.
來
How long will it take?
要量多久？
I'm still recovering, so it might take longer than usual.
我的病剛好，會比平常更花時間
I see.
這樣啊
What fabric would you like?
想選什麼布料呢？
I'll leave it to you.
交給你選吧
Well then,
那就選擇
how about a standard dark gray?
標準的深灰色吧
-Something like this. -Okay.
-大概這種顏色 -好
Now that I look closely, Nagisa does kind of resemble Junko.
仔細一看，渚跟純子長得真像
Excuse me.
我量一下喔
How long have you been a tailor?
你做這一行多久了？
For 33 years.
33年
Eighteen years in Kobe.
在神戶18年
And 15 years here.
搬來東京後15年
My father was strict, so it took me a while to go independent.
我爸很嚴格 一直不願意讓我獨當一面
But after five years, he finally told me to make a suit from scratch on my own.
不過在第5年時他終於答應 讓我從頭開始製作一件西裝
I wanted my very first suit
值得紀念的第一件
to be a gift for Junko's father.
我想送給純子的父親
So I gathered my courage
於是鼓起勇氣
and wrote you a letter.
寫了信過去
Please forgive
請原諒我
This sudden letter
突然寫信給你
Father, allow me
爸，請讓我製作
To gift you a suit
一套西裝送給你吧
Not an off-the-rack suit
並非市售品
But a custom-made one
而是訂製款
Please come to Kobe
想請你移駕到神戶來
So I can take your measurements
讓我幫你量尺寸
But I didn't come.
但是我沒來啊
Sorry about that.
真是不好意思
I think you know by now, but it's just who I am.
我想你應該明白，我是個固執的人
No, you came.
不，爸當時來了
Junko said she'd drag you if she had to.
純子說用拖的也要把你拖來
And she went to Tokyo to fetch you.
所以去東京接爸
Hey.
喂
What are you doing, geezer?
老頭，你在做什麼？
Let's go to Kobe.
跟我去神戶吧
Like hell, silly.
我才不去，笨蛋
You might say that,
嘴上在逞強
but you placed the letter on the butsudan.
卻把信好好供在佛壇上
I couldn't just toss it out.
我總不能丟掉吧
Come on, the taxi's waiting outside.
動作快，計程車在樓下等
I don't want to go.
我不想去
Nagisa wants to meet her grandpa.
渚也很想見到外公喔
Come on. Get in.
來，快進去吧
Father.
爸
Hey.
嗨
Nagisa, your grandpa from Tokyo is here.
渚，外公從東京來囉
Welcome.
歡迎光臨
Shoulder width
肩寬
Back width
背寬
Chest width
胸寬
Sleeve length
袖長
Center back sleeve length
後領至袖口的長度
Huh?
怪了
Sorry, I made a mistake.
我搞錯了，不好意思
Can I start over?
可以重來一次嗎？
Sure.
好
My lack of experience, coupled with intense nerves,
我因為不習慣，加上過度緊張
kept causing me to mess up and start over.
所以失敗並重來好幾次
Shoulder width
肩寬
You must be a pro with shoulders.
你很會量肩寬吧
Right, alien?
是不是？外星人
Chest width
胸寬
Wait, the back width comes first.
不對，要先量背寬才對
I forgot to take notes.
應該先寫筆記
Let's take a break.
等一下，我去抽根菸
Let's rest.
休息一下
I'm sorry, Father.
對不起，爸
It's fine.
沒關係啦
Don't worry about it.
別太在意
Come on, Nagisa.
來，渚
Sit on Grandpa's lap.
要不要讓外公抱？
Huh?
嗯？
Come on.
來嘛
Come here.
過來吧
Take a photo.
幫我們拍照
I held her?
我抱了她嗎？
I'm going to hold Nagisa?
我之後會抱到渚嗎？
This is the photo I took that day.
這就是當時的照片
By golly!
我的天哪！
That's a good photo!
好棒的照片！
When is this? How many years from now?
這是幾年後的事？
What is it? Again?
怎麼回事？你怎麼又來了？
January of 1995, huh?
1995年的1月？
In the end,
結果那天啊
by the time my father finished with the measurements, it was already late.
量完尺寸都已經是晚上了
And my grandfather missed the last train.
錯過末班車
So the three of them decided to go to a bar that stayed open all night.
只好三人一起在通宵營業的居酒屋
-And they killed time over drinks. -Thank you.
-邊喝酒邊消磨時間 -謝謝
She was a handful, let me tell you.
我這女兒真的很讓人頭疼
She was such a hussy.
是叛逆得要命的色小鬼
She was constantly after hanky-panky, I mean rumpy-pumpy.
抓到機會就打算滾床單 聽得懂嗎？就是做那檔子事
Shut up already.
少囉唆，知道了啦
Go to sleep. I'll wake you up.
你去睡覺，我會叫你起床的
No way, silly! I'm pulling an all-nighter.
我才不睡呢，笨蛋，我要熬夜到早上
SEIRYU
（清流）
Thank you.
謝謝招待
I'll walk him to the station.
那我送老爸去車站
All right.
好
Father, once your suit is ready, I'll come drop it off.
爸，西裝做好後我會送過去
Don't be silly. I'll pick it up myself.
別傻了，我會自己來拿啦
Not to see you guys.
我可不是為了來見你們
I'll come to see Nagisa.
是想來看渚
Sure. Bye.
好啦，先走了
Take care!
小心點喔
Hey, watch it.
幹什麼啦？
That…
那時候是…
was January 17th,
1月17日
5:46 a.m.
早上5點46分
Forgive me.
非常抱歉
If I hadn't been so slow with taking your measurements…
如果我不慢吞吞地量尺寸…
You and Junko would have survived.
爸和純子就會活下來
Does he
市郎先生
know about this?
知道那件事嗎？
I think
他大概…
he's finding out now.
現在才得知吧
We can't keep this from him forever.
這種事瞞不了多久的
I think he already knew.
他是不是早就知道了？
What?
什麼？
Remember?
你記得我們初次見面的那天嗎？
I wanted to show myself in a wedding dress to my father soon.
而且當時也想盡快讓父親看到我出嫁
My mother passed away in the year of the Great Hanshin earthquake.
我媽在阪神大地震那年過世了
The Great Hanshin earthquake?
阪神大地震？
When you don't know something, you just Google it, like this.
遇到不懂的問題時 只需要像這樣Google一下
See?
你看
What? Are you kidding me?
不會吧？這是怎麼回事？
1995? That's nine years from now.
1995年？不就是九年後嗎？
An earthquake that big?
日本會有這麼大的地震？
Huh, I see.
這樣啊，知道了
I'll keep that in mind.
謝謝你告訴我，我會牢記在心
When he found out that your mother was his own daughter,
當他知道你的母親就是他女兒的時候
he knew about her passing.
就察覺到她已經去世了
What?
什麼？
So he knew already
所以他明明知道
and played along with our lies?
卻假裝被我們騙到？
I see.
是嗎？
But I'm glad.
不過真是太好了
I was able to become friendly with you, patch things up,
我們最後有和解，把話說開
share some drinks, and hold my grandkid.
一起喝了酒，我還抱了孫女
I get to enjoy all that in the future.
在未來還有如此美好的事會發生
I'm looking forward to it!
令人期待呢！
So,
然後呢？
where's my suit?
西裝做好了沒？
Hey.
拿過來
Right.
好的
I'd brought it from Kobe.
我從神戶拿過來了
This is the first suit
這是我第一件
I tailored
親手縫製的西裝
A suit
為了爸所縫的
For my father
一套西裝
The first suit
這是我第一件
I am tailoring
親手縫製的西裝
A suit
為了爸所縫的
For my father
一套西裝
If your figure
你的體型
Is unchanged
如果都沒變的話
It's still the same
體型沒有變喔
It should suit you very well
一定會非常適合你
Hey.
嗨
What do you think?
好看嗎？
You look great.
很適合你
Of course, you do.
那當然啊
Dad made that suit.
畢竟這是爸做的西裝
You don't know? You're behind.
-你不知道嗎？那就落伍了 -很過時
When geezers can't find hope in the future,
如果無法對未來抱持希望
they start reminiscing about the past.
老頭就只好說些陳年往事
The only one allowed to mock my dad
能嘲笑我老爸的
is me, his daughter.
就只有我這個女兒啦
I'm back, Junko.
我回來了，純子
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻譯：樊穆妮